Why do they buy things they no longer had from their childhood?
为什么会买一些自己儿时不再拥有的东西呢
It's because they want to compensate for the psychological lack from their childhood.
就是因为他要补偿自己童年这种心理啊
You all know I bought a small scooter.
大家知道我买了一个小踏板
And I also got a small car.
还买了一辆小车啊
It can be called a microcar
可以说是微型车
specifically, an A00-class microcar
叫A00级的微型车
The total cost for this car was 33,600 yuan
这个车呢一共花了3万3600啊
We're not including insurance
保险咱们不算
In the future, when I buy a house
日后以后我去买房子
not when I trade in a car
不是买车的时候进行置换的时候呢
roughly, with the national subsidy
大概呢加上国补
along with other subsidies
加上补贴
the trade-in subsidy can amount to around 30,000 yuan
置换补贴也能折3万块钱左右
So basically, this car is practically free.
等于这车基本就没花钱啊
As everyone knows, my motorcycle is in the 10,000 range.
大家也知道我的摩托车也就是1万的水平啊
Actually, I initially planned to buy a motorcycle for around 6,000.
其实本来想买6000多的摩托车的
But then I thought, how much difference could there be between 6,000 and 10,000?
可是后来想6000跟1万能差多少呢
It’s mostly in the engine.
差不多就在发动机
So we decided to go with the original Suzuki engine.
所以咱们还是买铃木原厂的发动机啊
This will make future motorcycle trips more convenient.
这样以后摩旅方便一点
And the main reason for buying the UI125 is
而且买UI125的主要原因是
that it can be fitted with a sub-tank. Now that I've installed an auxiliary fuel tank, the car's range has reached 700 kilometers. My car's range is only 210 kilometers. It's very easy to turn on the air conditioning,
因为它能加装副油箱 我现在加装了副油箱以后呢 这个车的续航达到了700km 对我这个汽车的续航才210啊 实际很容易开会儿空调
and the range drops significantly.
它这个续航就掉啊
After I calculated it,
实际我测算了以后
driving about 60 kilometers,
开大概60km
the range can drop by about 100 kilometers.
它掉大概续航就能掉100啊
That's nearly half of it.
就能掉一半啊
Dropped by 105
大掉105啊
So basically, from the feeling in Beijing
所以呢基本上呢从北京那种感觉呢
If you need to go out
就是你要出去一趟
Even slightly
只要是稍微的
Like crossing the Fifth Ring Road
比如跨过东五环
The Fourth Ring Road
东四环啊
The Sixth Ring Road
东六环啊
You'd probably need to recharge for a round trip
就大概一来一回就得充一次电
But it's all good, I sorted out all the parking issues yesterday
不过还好昨天办妥了所有停车的事件啊
Let's also arrange the parking spaces in this residential area.
把这个小区的车位也排上了哈
Just arranged for 23 years.
刚排了23年
Then I also set up this roadside parking on Xueyuan South Road.
然后又办了这个学院南路的这个路边停车
So, you'll be able to see my car on Xueyuan South Road from now on.
大家以后在学院南路就能看到我这辆车了
But Xueyuan South Road is really long, you know.
但是整个学院南路呢非常长啊
Starting from the fourth intersection on the left of Xuanan South Road.
宣安南路的左起四道口
Both sides of this entire road, north and south, are my parking spots.
这整个这一条路的南北侧都是我的停车场
So this is a huge advantage.
所以这个就是一个非常好的一个优势啊
Parking in the city can be quite challenging.
啊住在城里停车难
But if you park it by the roadside, they can offer you an annual package, which is 3,600 for the year, 300 per month, which is quite good. Anyway, my current shopping experience is really great.
但是呢停在路边呢 他可以给你来一个包年的方式 相当于啊一年是3600啊 一个月是300块钱 挺好的啊 无论怎么说呢 我现在这个购物体验的是非常好
Why did I suddenly decide to buy a car?
为什么要突然买车呢
It's because I got the license plate quota in Beijing.
就是因为北京的指标下了啊
It was on May 28th.
5月28号下了
Actually, I need to buy a car before May 28th next year.
我实际上要在明年的5月28号之前要买车
But there are so many things to handle next year.
但是明年呢要操作的事情太多了啊
I’ll wait until my passport is renewed next year,
我明年等我护照更新以后
which will be after June.
就是6月以后更新
I might have to go back to Canada,
我可能要回一趟加拿大啊
or if everything goes well,
或者如果顺利的话
I might make a trip to Canada.
可能加拿大去一趟
And I'll be heading to the United States as well.
然后还要顺便去到美国啊
It will probably take about three or four months.
大概也就是三四个月的时间
I won't be staying for too long.
不会去太久啊
It's for work purposes.
啊工作需要啊
I'll be filming some content over there.
去那边拍拍东西啊
To keep you all updated with new stuff.
给大家更新点东西
So when you visit my channel,
这样大家看到我的这个节目的频道
There will be more content available.
内容就多了啊
For the rest of this year, I might focus on learning French.
我今年剩下的时间呢可能是用来学法语啊
Hehe, maybe it's about learning French
呵呵可能就是学法语
Then I'll be updating with a few new courses
然后会更新几个新的课程啊
Basically speaking
然后基本上来讲呢
The pace is about one update per month Why have I suddenly become more diligent recently It's because my work focus has started to shift Because now Gradually, I've found that In recent years, I've been thinking about developing overseas
每月一更新是这么一个速度呃 为什么最近突然开始勤劳呢 是因为我的这个工作重心开始变了啊 因为现在开始 逐渐的我发现就是嗯 近几年我是想往海外发展嘛
Actually, I've always planned to develop overseas in a few years.
啊其实一直都是打算就过几年就往海外发展
But now that there's the C11 work visa,
但是因为现在有这个C11的工作签证了
it might happen sooner.
所以来讲呢可能要提前了啊
If it happens sooner,
提前来讲的话
the benefit of this work visa is that
但是呢有这工作签证的好处
you don't have to stay for a mandatory period to qualify for residency.
就是就是啊你不用做移民监啊
You can go and stay for a month if you want to,
想过去待一个月就待一个月
or stay for four months if you prefer,
想过去待四个月就待四个月啊
or stay in the country for a year if you choose to.
想在国内待一年待一年啊
He doesn’t have too many time constraints.
他没有什么太长的时间限制
Just renew the work visa then.
你就续这工作签证的吧
So, the immigration step is skipped, right?
啊等于说就呃移民这一步都省了吧
Therefore, getting a work visa,
所以来讲的话拿一个工作签证
is also a pretty good compromise solution.
也是一个比较爽的一个折中的方案啊
At least you know that for this kind of work,
起码你能知道就是说作为这种工作来讲
for conducting international business,
你为了国际化的这种开展这种工作
there is actually a path you can take.
你实际上是可以有这么一条路径的
Without changing your current immigration status.
就是不改变你现当前这个移民身份
Without changing your nationality
不改变你这个国籍的这种状况下
you just apply for a work visa just like many foreigners apply for a work visa to come to China it’s the same principle it’s relatively reciprocal so, from my perspective
你只是申请工作签证啊 就像很多外国人申请来华的工作签证 是一个道理 这是相对的互互相对应 所以来讲的话就让我的感觉你看啊
speaking of North America
在北美来讲的话
I feel that Chinese Canadians particularly love driving SUVs
我觉得加拿大华人特别是爱开SUV
SUVs are so spacious
哎哎SUV又能装啊
It can carry cargo
又能装货
and show off too
又能装逼啊
In rural areas of America
在美国乡村地区
many people drive pickup trucks
很多人都开皮卡啊
In the colder eastern regions
在东部比较冷的地方
people also drive pickup trucks
大家也开皮卡
but I feel that driving a pickup is kind of
但我觉得开皮卡的话就比较呃
how should I put it
怎么说呢
many people just make their vehicles really big
很多人就是把自己的车弄得特别大
You'll find that
你会发现啊
in China, when I picked up my car and drove home the other day
国内来讲也是我说我那天取车回回家的时候
I was driving pretty fast
就是啊路上我开的比较快啊
so other motorcycles started to rev at me
所以呢就有其他的摩托就开始崩我
and even some SUVs did the same
然后又什么越野车呀也崩
I guess they can't stand someone driving faster than them
我就是他们忍受不了别人开的速度比自己快
the main reason was that a small scooter revved at me
主要的原因是因为是一个小踏板把自己崩了
which was really frustrating
所以特别难受
it's interesting how people's ego works
就是人的这个自尊心其实挺有意思
You'll find that a lot of times, people buy bigger cars
你会发现很多时候人买东西买更大的车
faster cars larger houses and it's often vanity that's driving these purchases So in reality how much of your life are you really spending on vanity on self-esteem, really?
买更快的车 买更大的房子 其实都是虚荣心在作怪 所以实际上来讲 你这辈子到底要为虚荣心 为自尊心要啊多付出多少啊
When I was in Canada
那会儿我在加拿大的时候
I felt that many people there really live their lives
我就感觉到很多那边的人呢是活的呢
Our way of speaking is quite simple and honest.
比较咱们说话呢比较淳朴啊
But I’m just a naive and sweet person.
但我说呢就是傻白甜啊
I haven’t gone through the gauntlet of exam-oriented education.
属于没有经过这个应试教育
Nor have I faced the harsh tests of competition in society.
跟这个竞争是社会的这种考验考验的人
He lives in a way that’s hard to describe,
他活的比较怎么说呢
but in a very natural state.
自然状态自然状态来讲
Look at those foreigners over there.
你看那边老外
Most of them drive a beat-up car worth a few thousand dollars,
基本来讲就是开个几千块钱的一个破车啊
usually an old Japanese or Korean model.
一个日韩系的破车
There are quite a few of them.
就是挺多的
It’s actually Chinese people who love buying sports cars.
反而是中国人特别爱买跑车
They love purchasing all sorts of large vehicles.
爱买各种各样的大车之类的
Mainly because they are in Canada,
主要还是因为在加拿大的
especially in Vancouver, where Chinese people are wealthy.
特别是在温哥华的中国人有钱啊
And you’ll notice that Americans really love big cars.
然后呢你看美国人呢就特别喜欢大车
big and noisy,
大的噪音大的
wasteful,
浪费的
large displacement vehicles are like that.
大排量的车都是这样
Americans are also quite concerned about saving face.
美国人比较也比较好面子啊
They value their reputation.
比较好面子
They place a lot of emphasis on appearances.
比较再注重门面啊
They care about respect.
注重这respect啊
You have to show me respect. Otherwise, I'll show you what I'm capable of. It starts like this, you might think it’s because Americans... To put it bluntly. Take a look. You're talking about Brother Rong, you never diss America in your show. That's not true.
你必须得给我respect 要不我就给你好看 就是这样开始你会觉得就是因为美国人 说白了 那你看啊 你说荣哥 你从来不在节目里边那个DISS美国 不是的
I often make comparisons.
我经常做比较啊
Americans are the vanguards of consumerism.
美国人是消费主义的急先锋
The term 'consumerism',
因为消费主义这个词啊
it originates from the United States.
啊就这个词就是从美国来的
It's about maxing out credit cards,
就是刷爆信用卡呀
and buying things that aren't suitable.
然买不合适的东西啊
Americans tend to do things like this.
就是美国人就容易干这种事啊
Of course, people from different states in America
当然美国不同州的人
have different spending habits.
地区的消费习惯也不一样啊
Some people buy pickup trucks for farm work,
当然来讲有些人他买皮卡是为了做农活啊
for hauling goods,
他为了运货
or for transporting livestock and such.
为了运那个牲口之类的
It's different, you see.
它是不一样的啊
But look, when it comes to Beijing,
但是你看我在北京来讲
I see many people buying pickup trucks.
就看到很多人买皮卡
I just wonder if it's for work
纯粹是我觉得是不是为了工作
or for show
是为了派头
And in Beijing, if you buy a pickup truck
而且在北京你买皮卡
you can use a trailer or an RV
你可以用拖挂房车啊
including a lot of other things with an RV
包括用房车用很多东西
In reality, I think
我觉得其实实际上来讲的话
we should follow a principle
我们去遵循它一个原则性的东西来讲
when you buy something
你买这个东西
why would you go for a particularly large engine size Why do you want to buy such a big car? I'm getting the Great Wall Cannon. It's all about face. It really has a lot to do with face.
为什么你要买特别大的排量 为什么你要买特别大的车啊 买长城炮啊 就是面子啊 真跟面子有很大的关系
But why do you always want to buy something bigger, stronger, and more robust?
但是你为什么内心里边老想买更大更粗更壮
Something more solid?
更结实的东西呢
It's because of your inner self.
是因为你的内心
Your confidence.
你的自信心啊
Your self-image.
你的自我形象啊
It feels a bit unstable
感觉呢有点不稳定啊
You need to let others know you're strong
你需要让别人知道你很强
You're very muscular
你很壮
You're very solid
你很结实
You can't afford to provoke others
你惹不起别人
They can't afford to provoke you
惹不起你
Do you know that
你知道吗
So that's the feeling
所以就是这种感觉
He makes others feel
他又让别人感觉到啊
You little scooter
你一小踏板
You dare to challenge me
你敢崩我
My car accelerates really fast
我我的车加速可快了啊
It's just that they can't handle this kind of inner
就是他们接受不了这种内自
challenge to their self-esteem
自尊心的这种挑战啊
even if you're just a bit faster
稍微比他快一点
he has to overtake you
他就一定要超过你
even if he has to switch lanes to do so
哪怕他并线超
Even if it's close to causing an accident, he'll still try to overtake you.
哪怕那种快饵差点出车祸那种超
He just has to overtake you.
他也要超过你啊
Even if it's entirely his fault,
就算他全责
He still has to overtake you.
他也要超过你
Hehe, it's quite amusing.
呵呵就是挺逗的
You'll find that men are particularly weak in this aspect.
你会发现男的就是这一点特别的弱啊
Men are very sensitive about their self-esteem.
男的就是在自尊心上面
When it comes to self-esteem, they just can't let it go. They have to be better than others in some way. Of course, look at this peacock. It's the male peacock displaying its feathers. What is he trying to do? This is a delayed form of courtship behavior.
这个这自尊心坚定就死活过不去啊 就一定要比别人怎么怎么样 当然来讲这个你看这孔雀啊 也是公孔雀在开屏啊 他为了要怎么样 他这是一种求偶行为的一种延后
Or we can say it's post-adolescent.
或者我们说这是青春期后至
So you'll notice these shopping tendencies.
所以你就会发现这个购物的这些倾向
They are linked to this.
是跟这个是联系在一起的
The more unstable your inner core is,
你的内心的内核越不稳定
the more you need material things to affirm yourself.
那你就越需要物质上的东西来肯定自己
Why do you want to buy a bag?
你为什么想买包啊
Why do you want to buy a car with a large engine?
你为什么想买大排量的车呀
Why do you want to buy a big house?
你为什么要买大房子呀
Is it because you feel a severe lack of material things inside?
是因为你内心里这种物质奇缺的这种感觉
It dominates your mind.
充斥着你内心
To put it bluntly, it's because you've experienced poverty.
说白了就是穷过囧国啊
Because you feel small.
自己小啊
Because you feel particularly insignificant.
自己那块儿特别小
And you become almost invisible, like a tiny teapot.
又又又跟小茶壶似的人看不见了
So you have to buy big things to show off yourself
所以你就必须买大大的东西来显示自己
Look how big I am
你看我多大我多大
I am big and strong
我又大又硬
But these things are external
但是这些东西它是外在的
They don't represent your true inner self
它不是你内心里真正你自己那个形象啊
This is often referred to as the small man syndrome
所以很多时这种叫小矮子综合症啊
Exactly
就是这样
Napoleon complex is when you feel shorter and less secure inside The weaker and softer you feel inside You need external things big cars with loud speakers high-displacement motorcycles
拿破仑综合症就是你内心里越矮越不稳定 越弱越软 你是需要外在的东西 大车大音响 大排量摩托啊
large houses
大房子
and fancy fashion items
然后包啊漂亮的时尚用品
to dress yourself up
然后去包装自己
I'm not a bumpkin
哎我不是村炮
I often see those on Douyin
你看我经常看到抖音上那些啊
so-called unscrupulous marketing accounts and self-media
所谓的无良营销号自媒体
Those hosts often
他们那些主持人经常啊
I’m not saying they are 3D people
不是我说就是3D人士啊
but they have low education
就是学历低啊
and low quality
这个这个素质低啊
let’s not even talk about the third low
那第三低咱就不说是什么低了啊
but you see, they dress in a certain way
反正就是你就看的都是那种人士穿的呢
all dressed up
人五人六
but once they open their mouths
但是那个口音一出来呢
you know right away
你就知道啊
This person must not have received much education.
这个人一定是没受过多少教育啊
They can't even speak Mandarin properly.
普通话都说不好
Of course, we're not saying that everyone who speaks poor Mandarin
就是当然咱不是说所有普通话说不好的人
hasn't been educated.
都是教育都是没教育的
You can't draw that kind of equivalence.
这种这个不能划等号
But people like this do tend to carry that kind of stereotype.
但是就这一类人他的确是有这种标签的啊
You'll notice the audience they face and they themselves belong to the same group. Clearly, they have the characteristics of 3D individuals. Let's talk about how to specifically define this 3D character. This is more about defining the style.
你会发现他啊面对的观众层啊 以及他自己都是同一类人 明显的就是那种3D人士这种特征啊 当然来讲具体这3D人士该怎么定义 这还是风格的定义方法
I won't speculate unnecessarily.
那我就不要妄加揣测了
But let me tell you,
但是我们跟你们说
the core of consumerism lies in its substantive content.
就是所谓的消费主义核心实在的内容
It stems from childhood trauma.
来自于童年的创伤
It comes from the instability in your inner core.
来自于你对自己内心内核的这种不稳定
It arises from your lack of confidence.
来自于你自己的不自信啊
Lack of self-reliance and self-respect.
不自强不自尊
Self-respect is something we give to ourselves.
自尊这个东西
If you give yourself enough respect,
self respect就是自己给自己的
you might think, 'I am beautiful',
如果你给自己了足够多的尊重啊
I am strong',
你觉得我很美啊
'I have a purpose in life',
我很强啊
'I have the ability to serve the people'.
天生我材必有用
At such times, you won't have any inner instability.
我有我能为人民服务的地方
This is a common belief.
这个时候你是没有什么内心不稳定的
There's a saying like this
这么一种说法
Generally speaking, where does inner instability come from?
通常来讲内心不稳定来自于什么呢
Your dad and mom criticize you.
你爸你妈说你啊
They say, 'Why are you like this?'
说你这怎么这么的嗯
You can't handle situations well.
不会处事啊
Look, yesterday when I interacted with someone,
你看我昨天我去跟人交流
When I was with my dad,
跟我爸走一块
I really get annoyed when I'm with my dad.
我就特烦我爸走一块
My dad always likes to lecture me.
我爸老爱教育我
But sometimes, his advice is right. Sometimes his way of teaching is not right. But I find it really annoying. He lectures me. Look, I’m 41 years old. And you’re still lecturing me? But to be fair, I do make some mistakes. His reminders do have their own merit.
但是呢有时候他教育的对 有时候呢他教育的不对 我但是我很烦 他教育我 你看我都41了 你还教育我啊 但是有时候来讲的话 确实我会犯一些错 他提醒的呢有有他自己的道理
Listen to your parents.
听父母的话
Just add half of it.
添一半就行了
Be filial, be filial.
孝顺孝顺啊
Being filial is enough.
孝就行了
Don't just obey.
不要顺啊
Show respect.
孝敬啊
Showing respect is enough.
敬就行了啊
You don't have to always obey them.
不用非得顺他
But sometimes parents are like that.
但是呢父母有时候就是这样啊
Some parents might say that.
他会有的父母呢来讲的话
My dad and mom still remind me
我爸我妈还是提醒我
When I make a mistake
我犯错了
They remind me
提醒我
But some people's parents
但是有些人的父母呢
Just completely overstep their bounds
就完完全全就是越俎代庖啊
Saying all sorts of things about how you're not good enough
各种各样的说你不好
You're not good-looking
你长得不好看
You won't be able to sell yourself this way
你这样的出去卖
And you're not smart enough to study like this
然后你这样的学习不聪明笨
You left the money at home
你把钱搁在家里
We all do this when we buy a house together
我们一块买个房子都是这样啊
So parents often try to belittle you
所以都是父母呢想方设法的那个贬低你啊
to undermine you
这个打击你啊
in order to control you
他为了控制你啊
that's how it is
就是这样啊
some bosses are like that too
有人那老板也是
that's why some people say
所以他为什么有人说啊
you can't buy a fancy car if you work for a state-owned enterprise
国企他那个公务员你不能买太好的车
That's it.
就是这样
Why can't you buy a really nice car?
为什么不能买太好的车
Because if your car is too nice,
因为你的车太好了
you'll make others feel inferior. So that's Brother Rong's strategy. I choose from all the motorcycles, my favorite one that can extend the range. And the small scooter with a 125cc engine can also handle the highway.
你把别人的自尊心比下去了啊 所以这就是荣哥的策略 我在所有的摩托里边买 我最喜欢的能够增加续航里程的摩托 然后呢小踏板呢125的排量呢又能上高速
But I don't usually use the highway.
哎我平时也不上高速
But the 725 with the small engine
但是呢一二版725的小排量呢
occasionally slipping into the bike lane
偶尔钻一下这个非机动车道
makes people think, 'Oh, it’s just like a scooter'
也让人感觉唉这不就一电瓶车嘛
no big deal
无所谓啊
if you were riding a 1250 over there
你要是开一个1250过去
wouldn’t it feel more significant to be on the motor vehicle lane?
那是不是坐在那个机动车道就显得很那什么
even if my 125 goes onto the sidewalk
我125哪怕上了人行道了
you can’t really say anything
你也不能说什么
right?
对不对
I just push it along.
我推着走就完了
And it’s very light.
而且他很轻
Really light.
就非常轻
It has the same weight as a skateboard.
跟踏板一样的质量
Right?
对不对
And speaking of which,
而且呢来讲的话
This mini, mini car is also my micro car.
我这个小型微微型车呢也是我的微型车
It’s super convenient to park anywhere.
到哪停车特方便
Just squeeze it in there.
往那一钻诶
People say it’s a toy for old men
人说这是老头乐吧
Yeah, at first glance, it looks like a toy for old men
哎一看以为是老头乐
But I’m afraid to bump into it
又不敢撞
You’re really amusing
你特别好玩
Because I thought there might be an old man inside the toy, right?
因为觉得你可能老头乐里边是老头对吧
Turns out it’s just a little old man
实际上也是一个小老头啊
Because parking is so convenient this way
因为这样停车又方便
And refueling is quick too
然后呢那个加油的也快啊
Charging takes only half an hour to be full
那个补电半个小时就满了
In reality, it's about reserving a car slot.
而实际上来讲呢就是占号车呃
You have to buy this slot, no way around it.
这个号不买不行
If I want to buy a BYD car,
你说我要买一个比亚迪
what would it cost? At least 60 to 90 thousand, 120 thousand for a car, that’s another chunk of money. No matter how much money you have, you’re still spending over ten thousand. That also takes up your wealth, doesn't it? A significant portion of it.
买一个怎么着 起码得6万9万啊 12万得买一个车 还得花一笔钱啊 无论你钱有多少 你花个十几万 那也占了你的财富的啊 那个啊很大一部分
Right?
对不对
So, buying a car for a station is pretty good.
所以来讲的话买一个站号车挺好啊
Actually, I don't really have the chance.
实际上我也没什么机会
There aren't many occasions to drive it.
没有什么场景去开
It doesn't take the kids anywhere.
它也不送孩子
And it's not for commuting.
也不上班
It's just a tool for entertainment, after all.
无非就是一个娱乐工具啊
Today, I went out for dinner with friends.
今天跟朋友吃饭去了啊
We drove out.
开出去了
Then, we had to find a designated driver first.
然后呢还得先找那个代驾
Recharge the battery first.
先补电
After recharging,
补完电
drive back.
然后再开回来啊
That's how it goes.
就是这样啊
A day of driving,
一天开车
a day of charging.
一天充电
It's just like this
就是这种
Although he finds it quite boring
他虽然他觉得很无聊
But he saved a lot of money
但是少花了很多钱
Because he saved a lot of money
少花了很多钱
Because my core values are very stable
因为我的内心内核是非常稳定的
I know exactly how much money I have
我知道自己有多少钱
I also know my capabilities
我也知道自己的能力是怎样
I'm also very satisfied with my current state
我也对自己的状态非常满意
I don't feel I owe myself anything
我也对自己没有任何的觉得亏欠的东西啊
All the things I feel I've been lacking
所有亏欠的来讲呢
I might have some things I feel I've been missing out on
可能我有些是亏欠
Like not having enough toy guns when I was a kid
比如说我小时候玩具枪不够啊
Growing up, I wanted to go to North America
我长大想去北美啊
To buy more stuff
再买点什么啊
Like water guns and such
喷子之类的
These things are probably what I missed out on in my childhood But speaking of what's available here in China I have more than enough I'm very content. Considering my current state, I don't feel like there's anything missing in my life. I've bought all the gaming consoles I could want.
这些东西可能是我的这个童年的缺失 但是在国内来讲 我的更多满足的啊 我是非常满足的 我现在的整个状态来讲 我觉得我生活中没有什么缺的东西了啊 游戏机能有的我都买了
Right?
对不对
I've got all the electronic gadgets I need.
所有的电子产品我都买了啊
I have a pile of books.
书我有一大堆啊
I don't really care about cars or houses.
车房子这些东西我不在乎啊
As long as I have a place to live, that's fine.
房子有地儿住就行了
As long as the car can move, that’s fine.
车它能动就行啊
As long as it can move.
能动就行
I’ll go with Latam.
我图拉丁吧
It’s already level 13.
都13级了
For me, as long as it can move, that’s all I care about.
你想这些东西对我来讲能动就行
So today, we’re going to delve into something deeper.
所以我们今天引申出来一个
Something on a more profound level.
这个更深层次的东西
It’s not about pride.
不在于自尊心
It’s not about anything else.
不在于什么
What is the goal of your lifelong struggle?
就是你这一生你的奋斗的目标
With all this effort you're putting in,
你这样的努力
What is it all for?
你到底是为了什么
Buddy,
哥们儿
What is it for?
你是为了什么
Why do you need to earn so much money?
就是你是为了什么要去挣这么多钱
Why do you have to live a 9-to-5 life,
要这么着朝九晚五的
Or even a 996 lifestyle,
或者说996的生活
What's the purpose of earning money?
你挣钱的目的
Can the money you earn cover
你挣的这个钱能不能满足
the 2,000 calories you need each day
每天2000大卡的这个热量
If the money you earn is enough to support your family
如果你挣的钱足以糊口养家
then what's the purpose of saving money? Sun Yuchen has a book the content in that book is quite similar to some of mine it's actually pretty close Of course, I'm not as impressive as Teacher Sun Teacher Sun is truly amazing
然后你攒钱的目的是什么啊 孙雨辰就有一本书 他里边那本书跟我的一些书的内容 其实挺接近的啊 当然来讲我没有孙老师那么牛逼 孙老师那是真是啊
He's quite remarkable among people.
人中龙凤挺牛逼的
He has a piece of paper that says he won't get married.
他有一部有一张他就写不结婚
He doesn't buy a house or a car.
不买房不买车
How do I spend my days?
我的日子是怎么过的
I noticed that all these people who want to build a career,
诶我发现所有的这些啊想搞事业的人
actually have this mindset of not getting married,
其实都有这种不结婚
not buying a house or a car.
不买房不买车的这种啊
This kind of thinking is
这种认知在
because it's essential not to let your salary and a so-called
因为就是不能让工资和一份所谓
A stable job ties you down
稳定的工作绑持了
It binds you tightly
你把你绑实了
You no longer have the vision for innovation and expansion
你就不再具有啊任何创新的拓展视野的
Or the mindset to start a business
开创事业的思维了
I mean, these cars
也就是说你的这些车啊
Xiaomi Ultra S7
小米ultra苏七
These houses
你的这些房
Is it really worth sacrificing your youth for these ready-to-move-in large apartments?
这种现成大平层到底值不值得你付出青春啊
Putting everything on the line and tying yourself to a job
付诸一切还得绑定工作
Binding the address
绑定住址啊
Striving for everything
为之奋斗一切啊
It ultimately is just a purchase
最终也就是个消费
That feeling fades away in an instant
那个感觉一下瞬间就过去了啊
Like how I managed to get a motorcycle and a car within a week In the end, the sense of ownership feels pretty good But I didn’t spend much The amount I spent This 40,000 yuan to me
你像我一星期之内搞定了摩托车跟这个汽车啊 最后呢我拥有的感觉呢也挺美 但是我没花多少钱啊 我花的这点钱 这4万块钱对我来说呃
It's not that this 40,000 yuan isn't money
也不能说这个4万块钱不是钱
But for me
但是对于我来说
This amount, in half a month, yeah
这点钱这个嗯半个月嗯
Not to mention half a month
别说半个月了
I could probably earn it in a week
可能一个星期就赚到了
Yeah, of course, that's true
就是啊当然也呗行
Don't brag, can you do it in a month?
别别吹牛逼啊啊一个月一个月行不行
Let's not talk about half a month
咱别说半个月
Not even a week
别说一个星期
Let's just say when business isn't doing well
咱就说生意不好的时候啊
I still manage to make some money in a month
一个月哎也赚到了
So for me, it's not a huge hit
所以对我来说就是不会那么伤筋动骨啊
It's not a major setback
不会那么伤筋动骨
It's not like I have to dip into my savings
不会说又动用了财富之类的
But you'll find that many people take out car loans for a few ten thousand dollar cars
但很多人你会发现他啊车贷买个几10万的车啊
At least three or four hundred thousand, and they're paying it off over three to five years
起码三四十万后还个5年三年的车贷
And they also owe the bank over a million for their mortgage
房贷也是欠着银行100多万
In the end, it's just one house
你最终也是一套房子
A car, you know
一辆车呀
how much of a difference can there be?
能有多大的区别呢
And when I had a small car
而且我拥有小车的时候
every time I took a taxi
我每次去打车
every time I rode in someone else’s car
每次坐别人的车
I always thought the car was so big You get it? Like when I said I got married my wife used to scold me a lot All the girls I met later I thought they were so patient
我都觉得这个车好大呀 明白吗 就像我以前我说我结婚的时候呃 那个老婆老骂我啊 后来我遇到的所有女孩子 我觉得别人脾气真好呀
Each one of them was so pleasant and had great emotional control
一个个的这么和颜悦色的情绪控制的非常好
It's because you've had something before
这就是你拥有过一件东西
You bring it up
你就拿它来啊
Of course, people are not objects
当然来讲人不是东西啊
It's about something you've had
就是拥有过的东西啊
The state of having had something
拥有过的这个状态吧
You tend to use it for comparison
你就会拿出来做做比较
You should have a really nice car
你要拥有一个特别好的车
You should live in a spacious apartment
你要家里住的大平层啊
I come from a wealthy family
我是一个富家子弟
It's easy to go from frugality to luxury
由俭入奢易
But it's hard to go from luxury back to frugality
由奢入俭难
You guys always have a Maybach at home
你天天你们家就迈巴赫了
What kind of car will you ride when you go out
你出去以后坐什么车
You'll feel like everything else is just a toy
你都觉得是玩具
It will all feel awkward
都觉得别扭
Everyone thinks it smells like plastic
都觉得有塑料味
You're eating Michelin-starred cuisine every day
你天天吃的米其林
If you go out and eat from street vendors
你出去吃街边摊
You might not be able to handle it
你可能受不了
You're used to living in luxury apartments with five-star standards
你天天住的都是五星级标准的大平层啊
Spending two or three million on the renovation
装修花个两三百万
Where would you stay after going out, in some budget hotels?
你出去以后住哪什么便便携酒店
You wouldn't be able to stay there
你是住不了的
Brother Rong is suffering
荣哥苦啊
I've been through tough times,
我苦过啊
like when I was studying abroad, it was hard too.
说留学的时候也苦过
So now, when I taste a bit of sweetness,
所以我现在感受一点点甜
I feel it's really damn sweet.
我就觉得真他妈的甜
You know?
知道吗
That's how it is.
就是这样
That's the experience of life. People always talk about raising boys with hardships, and girls with abundance and comfort. That's not entirely true. From a human perspective, You start with the bad,
所以这就是人生的体验 老说什么男孩穷养 女孩富养之类的啊 这不要那么绝对 这个从人的角度来讲的话 你先拥有差的
Or what you have is bad,
或者你拥有的是差的
But it can make the world feel so much better.
能让这个世界感觉特别好啊
Why do I keep telling everyone,
我为什么老跟大家说说
Why does Brother Rong only wear a tank top,
荣哥为什么就穿一个背心
Why never talk about putting on a persona in front of the camera,
为什么永远不会说在这个在镜头面前做人设
Or setting up a study background
也不弄个书房背景
Not inviting big names
也不请大咖
Just being myself like this
就是自己就是这样
Then showing this big face
然后就照着这么一个大脸
That's how it is
就这么着
I do it this way every time
每次都这么做
Because my starting point was low
因为我的起点低以后
I just need to raise the bar a bit
我稍微拔高一点
I might invite someone to do a bit of makeup
我稍微请个人稍微化妆化妆
Do a bit of sound design
稍微的声音声音之类的设计一下
The whole feel is just different now.
这个整个感觉就不一样了
My starting point is this little step.
我的起点就是这么一个小踏板
It's a small electric scooter.
就是一个小电动车
Number 9.
9号啊
A tiny step, right?
一个小小踏板对吧
Then there's this little panda knight car.
然后一个小小熊猫熊猫骑士小车
So no matter what I have in the future,
所以我以后无论拥有什么
I'll always compare it to this starting point.
都会以这个起点相比较
I know I came out riding an electric scooter.
我明白我是骑电动车出来的啊
So I believe I shouldn’t have something that’s overly good or overly expensive which means my maintenance costs are relatively low giving me more time
所以来讲我就认为我不应该拥有特别特别好 特别特别贵的东西 所以我相对的维持费就小 所以我就会有更多的时间
and more energy to make money
更多的精力去赚钱啊
and when I talk about making money
而我赚钱来讲话
I don’t feel it’s ever enough
我不会觉得不够
because many people earn money to fuel their consumption
因为很多人赚钱的目的是为了我要消费
you know, I had a girlfriend before
你看我有一个啊前女友吧
He's making a lot of money now.
就是他现在赚钱赚的多啊
But he's really wearing himself out.
给自己累的够呛啊
He works incredibly hard.
是干的活干的非常辛苦的一个人啊
Actually, he earns quite a bit.
他赚的其实挺多的
To be honest, at the moment,
现在应该算是说实在的
There have been a few months where he's earned more than me.
有有几个月都比我多啊
Honestly,
说实在的
Of course, I don't do anything at all.
当然我是压根屁事不干
He works himself to the bone every day.
他是天天累死累活
This can't be compared.
这个不能相比较
But he was in his youth,
但是他就是年轻时候
he had so many wonderful things.
拥有过太多太好的东西了啊
His ex-boyfriend was very wealthy.
非常富有的前男友啊
Very beautiful items.
非常漂亮的东西
Everything from food to clothing was of good quality.
吃的穿的这一套东西都有好的
So her goal is to be an independent woman,
所以她的目的就是我独立女性
I want to have these things.
我要拥有这些东西啊
So I need to work hard and earn money.
所以我要赚钱努力
I just find him quite ridiculous, to be honest.
我就觉得在我眼中他就比较可笑嘛
Of course, I’ll keep encouraging her. To buy things she likes. In the past, other men would buy things for you. Now you can buy them yourself, showing your capability. But I just want to point this out. These things don’t define you; you’re already very attractive.
就是当然我也会一直鼓励她啊 去买自己喜欢的东西啊 以以前让别的男人给你买 现在自己买自己有本事 但是我就是说点破这一点 就是这些东西他不代表你你本人已经很好看了
You’d still be very attractive without these things.
你没有这些东西你也很好看
You’ve always been quite attractive.
你一直都挺好看的
Right?
对不对
So the difference between being able to afford these luxury items and not being able to afford them is not that significant.
所以这个东西就是你买得起这个这些奢侈品
In the end, you work so hard,
跟买不起这些奢侈品对你的区别意义不大
I hope he can reinvest it in production.
最终你努力了半天啊
Completely stop working.
我是希望他能投入到再生产当中
But he might first invest in a car,
彻底不劳动
a bag,
但是他可能会先投入到车啊
These things help people feel good about themselves.
包啊
These things make one feel good about themselves
这些东西让人看得起自己
That's quite amusing.
这就挺逗的了
She's already a stunning beauty.
就是她已经是一个大美女了
But this thing, it's different for boys and girls.
所以但是这个东西呢男孩女孩不一样啊
We shouldn't advise women,
咱们不能去劝女性
especially independent women.
特别是独立女性啊
We can help them in their careers,
事业上可以给人帮忙
but how they spend their money
但是人家怎么花钱
is their business.
那是人家的事
But I just wanted to point that out.
但是我就是点明这一点
Whether male or female
无论男性还是女性
I actually see myself as gender-neutral
我其实是把自己看成是中性的
I consider myself to be genderless Because I don’t have the typical flaws of either men or women I don’t have them For instance, men spend money to satisfy their ego And women spend money to satisfy their vanity To be honest
我自己其实是把自己看成是无性别的 因为我男性那些毛病我没有女性的毛病 我也没有 就是说男的为了自尊心 女的为了虚荣心花的这个钱 说实在的
This could make your work extremely painful
就是这一点有可能让你劳动的非常的很痛苦
For example, if you make a million dollars
你想你比如说你赚了100万
you can use that million to hire people
你把这100万用来雇人
to expand production
用来扩大生产
and you might completely step away from labor
你可能完全就脱离劳动
but if you spend that million on a Cayenne
但是你这100万你买一辆卡宴
isn't it gone?
不就他妈没了吗
Isn't it gone?
不就没了吗
Isn't it gone, buddy?
哥们不就没了吗
then you have to earn another million
然后你再挣100万
which could scare the hell out of you
你吓死你
can you even make another million?
100万你挣得来吗
You've traded your youth and labor for it
你用青春用劳动力换来的
your time
用时间
your health
用健康换来的
do you think a million will always be that easy to earn?
你以为100万永远都那么容易赚吗
Earning a million at 20
你20岁时候赚100万
is different from 30
跟30岁
50 or 60, can it be the same?
50岁60岁能一样吗
Buddy
哥们儿
you need to figure out how to make money with money
你以后得想办法用钱赚钱
right?
对不对
exploit surplus value
剥削剩余价值
and have employees help you make money
然后用人让员工帮你挣钱
you need to set goals for your employees
你要给员工画饼
you can't do everything yourself
你哪能都自己干呢
so this is a huge conflict in mindset
所以这就是一个巨大的观念的一个冲突
that's what we're talking about here
所以我们这是这一说
in this episode, we mainly talk about spending less spending less means you won't be so tired it's a simple and obvious truth Brother Long contributes this to you today, before starting the renovation before the drill starts
这一期我们主要说的就是消费少 消费你就不会那么累啊 就这么简单一个浅显的道理 龙哥贡献给你啊 今天在装修开始 这电钻开始之前啊
we made this episode
做了这一期
hoping everyone has a happy day every day
希望大家每一天都天天快乐
keep your desires small
欲望小小的啊
don't compare with others, keep your inner core stable
不要跟人去比欲望小小的内核稳定的
take care of your health
保证好自己的健康
keep your core stable and the external things
内核稳定一些外在的东西啊
keep your desires small
欲望小一些
it's fine
没事呢
read the classics of Taoism
看看道家的经典
read the classics of Buddhism
看看佛家的这些经典
to make your mind more peaceful, adopt an indifferent and carefree attitude
是不是让自己的内心平和一些平常心啊
experience this impermanent world
感受这个无常的世界
clear your mind of consumerism
消费主义的脑子清凉一些
watch less ads
少看广告啊
buy a smaller car
买小一小的车
a smaller motorcycle
买小小的摩托
live in a smaller home
住个小小的家
right?
对不对
marry a simple wife
娶个小小的媳妇
have a simple child
生个小小的娃
it won't cost as much
没那么花钱啊
buying a big house
买大大的房子
a big car
大大的车
big things actually cost a lot
大大的这些东西其实很花钱啊
consumerism means the more stable your inner core is the more stable your self-esteem is the more stable your vanity is the less it will trigger your desire to consume and working to satisfy consumption desires is a very miserable life
消费主义就是你内心里边儿越稳定啊 你的内核越稳定你的自尊心啊 虚荣心越稳定 他越不会激起你的消费欲望 而为了消费欲望去工作 去劳动的一生是非常非常凄惨的啊
having small desires can make you less tired
欲望小能让自己很不受累啊
see what kind of desires
你看什么样的欲望
the smaller your desires are
都是你的欲望越小
the less your body is strained
你的身体越不受累
the longer your life will be
你的寿命越长
the more you can appreciate the beauty of life
越能感知这个人生的美妙
of course, speaking of which
当然来讲的话
buying a new car
买新车
a new motorcycle
买新摩托
a new house is still very joyful
买新房子还是很开心
but the joy only lasts a week
但是开心也就那么一个礼拜